בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's דף daf is ה, Hey, and we
pick up in the middle of a fascinating discussion about נזיר שמשון
Nazir Shimshon and נזיר עולם, Nazir Olam, and we pick up at
the bottom of ד עמוד ב, Daled amud beis, and we are
ושמשון
לאו נזיר הוה, v'Shimshon lav nazir havae, which is one, two, three,
four, five, seven lines from the bottom.
So the גמרא Gemara says, like the whole question here was whether
שמשון Shimshon accepted the נזירות nezirus himself or not, and whether it
was a classic like נזירות nezirus that came through a vow, that
came through a נדר, neder, so therefore is it possible to extend
it to yourself?
Do you have the mechanism of creating נזיר שמשון? Nazir Shimshon? A
debate of the תנאים. Tannaim. So the גמרא Gemara now says, ושמשון
לאו נזיר הוה, v'Shimshon lav nazir havae, and was שמשון Shimshon not
a נזיר? nazir? Now that's והכתיב. v'ha-ksiv. Now of course that's a
funny question; nobody said he wasn't a נזיר. nazir. The question was
whether he had done it through a vow
and the problems that that created.
But the גמרא Gemara assumes, well, let's see the question. והכתיב, v'ha-ksiv,
doesn't the verse say כי נזיר אלהים יהיה הנער מן הבטן, ki
nezir elohim yihye hana'ar min habaten,
that the child will be a נזיר nazir to God from the
womb? So you see he was a נזיר. nazir. גמרא Gemara says,
no, התם מלאך דקאמר, hasam malach d'ka-amar, no,
that was just the angel that was saying. Now to fit this
into the previous discussion, we'd have to say that the question was,
didn't he accept the נזירות nezirus through a נדר? neder? Because that
was the problem we had
yesterday, that it didn't come about through a נדר. neder. So how
is that supposed to demonstrate
that
he accepted his נזירות nezirus in the normal way? Because that's what
he would have done. And the answer is, no, it was just
what the angel said. But more simply, I think this גמרא Gemara
might be reading the debate of רבי יהודה ורבי שמעון Rebbi Yehuda
and Rebbi Shimon like I think the impression one initially gets. If
you go back and you remember what רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon says,
it's like five lines from the top to remind you, it says
רבי שמעון אומר האומר נזיר שמשון לא אמר כלום שלא מצינו בשמשון
שיצאה נזירות מפיו. Rebbi Shimon omer ha'omer nazir Shimshon lo amar klum
shelo matzinu b'Shimshon sheyatza nezirus mipiv. Right, he never said that he
would be a נזיר. nazir. Now that could be read in one
of two ways. He was a נזיר, nazir, but it was not
through a vow, and therefore you can't transfer it. That's the way
the גמרא Gemara read it yesterday. Or you could read it that
רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon is saying he never was a נזיר. nazir.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, what do you mean he never
was a נזיר? nazir? The angel says he was a נזיר. nazir.
And then the answer is, no, that was the angel sort of
directing, but it doesn't mean that he actually ultimately had that formally
as a halachic status. All right, anyway, that is wrapping up the
point of yesterday, that שמשון Shimshon according to רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon
either was a נזיר nazir but it didn't come through a vow
and therefore it cannot be transferred, or maybe the גמרא Gemara is
hinting at an idea that maybe according to רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon
he was not a נזיר nazir at all, at least not a
halachic נזיר. nazir. Now the גמרא Gemara continues, ומנא ליה דאיטמי למתים?
u'minah d'itmei l'meisim?
Now how do you know that if there is this thing called
נזיר שמשון Nazir Shimshon and you are able to sort of make
yourself into a נזיר שמשון Nazir Shimshon through, let's say, transferring שמשון's
Shimshon status onto you, if that's the mechanism as we learned yesterday,
how do you know that that has an allowance for becoming טמא?
tamei? Where do you know that שמשון Shimshon ever became טמא מת?
tamei meis? He certainly killed a lot of people, but how do
you know he directly touched them? So the גמרא Gemara says, אילמא
מדכתיב, ilema m'dichsiv, if you say it's from the verse בלחי החמור
הכיתי אלף איש, lechi hachamor hikeisi elef ish,
with the jawbone of an ass I slew a thousand men. So
if they're hitting them with that, you're coming in contact with them.
And then it gets interesting questions about טומאה בחיבורין, tuma b'chiburin, if
you didn't touch them directly with your body but you touched them
through something else. But if you're getting that close to slay them
with the jawbone of an ass, so then presumably you came in
contact. So the גמרא Gemara says, דילמא גירוי גרו ביה, dilma giruy
garu beih,
maybe he threw it at them. He tossed it. Maybe it was
a boomerang or something and he had to retrieve it. Anyway, maybe
he threw it at them and he never actually touched them. All
right, so you can't prove that he touched them. אלא מהכא, ela
meihacha, from here: ויך מהם שלשים איש ויקח את חליצותם, vayach mehem
shloshim ish vayikach es chalitzosam, and he smote from them thirty men
and he removed their tunics, their garments.
So if you're going to go ahead and remove their garments after
they're dead, you're going to come in contact with them. So the
גמרא Gemara says,
maybe he first got them to undress and then he killed them,
so he didn't have to come in contact with them after he
killed them. So the גמרא Gemara says, ויך ויקח כתיב. vayach vayikach
ksiv. No, it says he smote and he took; he took it
after he smote them. Although how are you going to get them
to
cooperate the
other way? Anyway, ודילמא גוססין שוינהו. v'dilma gosesin shavinahu. So you can't
prove he actually touched them when they were dead. אלא פיין גמרא
גמירא לה, Ella fayn, gemara gemira lah, that's a tradition we have
that שמשון Shimshon actually came in contact with some of the people
that he killed. Alright, so that's the end of נזיר שמשון. Nazir
Shimshon. Then the גמרא Gemara says like this, ונזיר עולם היכא כתיב,
V'nazir olam heicha ktiv, where does the פסוק pasuk mention the idea
of a נזיר עולם, Nazir Olam, that we have this concept that
somebody that's a, again, not just somebody's choosing not to terminate their
נזירות, nezirut, but the nature of the נזירות nezirut is that it's
a permanent state and that actually gives an allowance to cut the
hair periodically? So the גמרא Gemara says,
דתניא ותנא ברייתא רבי אומר אבשלום נזיר עולם היה. Detanya, v'tana b'raisa
Rabbi omer: Avshalom Nazir Olam hayah. The same way we learned out
this idea called נזיר שמשון Nazir Shimshon from a story in תנ"ך,
Tanach, we learn out this idea of נזיר עולם Nazir Olam from
a story in תנ"ך. Tanach. אבשלום Avshalom was a נזיר עולם, Nazir
Olam, right? Because of the whole story about him getting caught up
in the tresses of his hair by the tree and so on,
שנאמר ויהי מקץ ארבעים שנה. shene'emar: Vayehi miketz arba'im shanah. What was
that after forty years? And this was when אבשלום Avshalom was basically
plotting the, you know, to the rebellion against his father against King
David. שנה ויאמר אבשלום אל המלך אלכה נא ואשלם את נדרי אשר
נדרתי לה' בחברון, Shanah, vayomer Avshalom el hamelech: Elchah na va'ashalem et
nedarai asher nadarti l'Hashem b'Chevron, and he said to the king: Let
me go and I will satisfy my vow that I made to
God in חברון. Chevron. ומגלח אחד לשנים עשר חודש, Umegalach echad l'shneim
asar chodesh, and we know that he would cut his hair once
every twelve months according to רבי Rebbe that says it's once every
twelve months, שנאמר ויהי מקץ
ימים לימים, shene'emar: Vayehi miketz yamim l'yamim, and it was from the,
from you know, from days to days at the end of that.
And that's understood, so the assumption here that's being read into the
פסוקים, pesukim, it's not literally in the פסוקים, pesukim, is fulfill my
vow. Since we're going to say that a נזיר עולם Nazir Olam
cuts their hair, when they choose to cut their hair they do
it by bringing the three קרבנות korbanot that normally terminate נזירות, nezirut,
so sort of the idea is with them you don't get to
terminate your נזירות nezirut but you bring these קרבן korban and they
sort of open up, you know, create an opening for you and
an allowance for you to cut your hair. So when אבשלום Avshalom
is saying I've gotta go satisfy my vows, that means I've gotta
go bring the קרבנות korbanot that are going to allow me to
cut my hair. All of this is being read into the פסוקים,
pesukim, okay, but that's how we're choosing to read these פסוקים. pesukim.
And it was done at the end of ימים לימים, yamim l'yamim,
days to days, which we're going to say means on an annual
year basis he would do this. He would bring these נדרים, nedarim,
these vows, these קרבנות, korbanot, and therefore be allowed to cut his
hair. Okay, ויליף, v'yalif, top of עמוד א', amud aleph, ימים ימים
מבתי ערי חומה, yamim yamim mibatei arei chomah, and רבי Rebbe learns
a connection of the word ימים yamim here to where it says
ימים yamim by houses in a walled city. מה התם, Ma hasham,
the same way there it says י"ב חודש, yud-bet chodesh, that we
say there it says, right, that a person sells a house in
a walled city he's got a year to buy it back, and
if he doesn't buy it back then he loses it permanently, he
doesn't even get it back in the יובל. yovel. And there the
תורה Torah says explicitly that it says that the תורה Torah says
עד מלאת לו שנה תמימה, ad melot lo shanah temimah, until one
full year has completed. Okay, so it uses the word ימים yamim
there and it uses the word, what's the whole פסוק? pasuk? The
whole פסוק pasuk is, let me see,
ימים תהיה גאולתו, yamim tihyeh ge'ulato, his גאולה ge'ulah will be for
ימים, yamim, and then it speaks of if he doesn't redeem it
עד מלאת לו שנה תמימה ad melot lo shanah temimah and if
he doesn't redeem it at the end of a full year. So
you see it's identifying you can redeem it for the duration of
ימים yamim and you have until the end of a full year,
so the word ימים yamim means a full year. Got that? It
says ימים, yamim, okay. So ויליף ימים ימים מבתי ערי חומה מה
התם י"ב חודש אף כאן י"ב חודש, v'yalif yamim yamim mibatei arei
chomah, ma hasham yud-bet chodesh, af kan yud-bet chodesh, the same way
there you have a ימים yamim to redeem it means twelve months,
a full year,
אף כאן af kan it also means it. So אבשלום Avshalom is
our model, he would do it periodically ימים לימים, yamim l'yamim, we're
reading in he would bring these קרבנות, korbanot, he would cut his
hair. We know he had this very long hair, he was a
נזיר, Nazir, that's what we're assuming and so on, and therefore that's
how we get this idea. It was pointed out to me yesterday
that it's interesting again because we ended yesterday with the story about
the guy who became a נזיר Nazir in order to cut his
hair, and we talked about the contrast to that to the משנה
Mishnah that a person grabs his hair the way שמואל Shmuel reads
it and says I will be beautiful and that means I'll be
a נזיר. Nazir. So is the long hair, is it supposed to
be beautiful נזיר, Nazir, growing the hair long, right, or is it
supposed to be a bad thing because you have to cut your
hair in the end? And again it's quite ironic because I would
say פשט pshat of the פסוקים pesukim is the reason you פרע
pera as I said like the hair grows wild and that makes
you seem like, you know, like unkempt and not fit within normal
society. So someone pointed out to me yesterday, you know, that the
אבשלום Avshalom example also is one in which the hair is described
in תנ"ך Tanach as something very beautiful. So it's an interesting question
about right whether the נזיר Nazir and the hair is seen as
something very beautiful or something that actually makes them something of an
outcast. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, so that's
רבי Rebbe who says a
year. Actually what I'm going to do is Dov asked me to
apologize because he somehow lost the list. I'm glad to see I'm
not the only one who loses things and that we did yesterday,
so I'm going to pass this around again. Unfortunately we don't have
the... The נזיר Nazir and the hair is seen as something very
beautiful or something that actually makes them something of an outcast. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says like this. So that's רבי Rebbi who
says a year. Actually, what I'm going to do is דוב Dov
asked me to apologize because he somehow lost the list. I'm glad
to see I'm not the only one who loses things, and that
you did yesterday. So I'm going to pass this around again. Unfortunately,
we don't have everybody here, but let's at least try to start
reconstructing the list. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. So
that's how רבי Rebbi gets a year. רבי נהוראי אומר, Rabbi Nehorai
omer, רבי נהוראי, Rabbi Nehorai, now we're going to see a debate
about how frequently a נזיר Nazir can cut his hair. רבי נהוראי
אומר Rabbi Nehorai omer מגלח אחת לשלושים יום megale'ach achas lishloshim yom
every thirty days, which is, you know, it's a pretty big allowance.
Here guy's a נזיר Nazir for life, and every thirty days he's
allowed to get a trim. Okay, he doesn't get to cut his
hair all off, but he's allowed to get a trim, but, you
know, he's basically patterning it after that's the standard duration of נזירות.
nezirus. So even though your נזירות nezirus goes for forever, after you've
done a standard like, you know,
unit of נזירות, nezirut, you get an allowance to cut your hair.
Okay, so that's what he says. מגלח אחת לשלושים יום. megale'ach achas
lishloshim yom. רבי יוסי אומר, Rabbi Yosi omer, רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi
is even more radical. מגלח מערב שבת לערב שבת. megale'ach me'erev Shabbos
le'erev Shabbos. You get to cut every ערב שבת, erev Shabbos, שכן
מצינו בבני מלכים שמגלחים מערב שבת
לערב שבת, shekein matzinu bivnei melachim shemegalchim me'erev Shabbos le'erev Shabbos, because
princes, אבשלום Avshalom here was a prince, so obviously he must have
cut his hair frequently enough that he would seem like presentable as
a prince. So clearly learning from the model of אבשלום Avshalom we
have to assume that he would cut his hair every week. Of
course, this is completely strange. Number one is, if he trimmed his
hair every week, how's the תורה Torah describing, the נביאים Nevi'im describing
that he had such long hair and it got caught in the
trees and all that whole thing, number one? And number two, so
even if, so are we saying that since that must have been
the case by אבשלום Avshalom then any normal person who accepts נזירות
עולם nezirus olam gets to do it on a weekly basis? That's
also a little bit strange. Okay, maybe we have to be consistent,
but it's pretty strange I think to sort of just assume that
that was true by אבשלום Avshalom even when the פסוקים pesukim indicate
otherwise.
The hair doesn't have to be that thick. No, it's not that
thick a hair. Why? In the end it's the
split ends that they trimmed, that's all. Okay, if you say that,
oh, so you're saying that if he's doing it every week,
he's not doing a serious haircut, he's only doing it a little
trim. Okay, maybe, maybe. The other interesting thing I would ask is,
one minute, if I say I'm a נזיר Nazir and I have
to wait thirty days, right, so then I have to be מגדל
פרע, megadel pera, the hair has to grow for thirty days, less
than that it's not considered מגדל פרע, megadel pera, right? So we're
going to see that in a minute, that's one of the bases
we know that it's thirty days. It's not significant hair growth until
then. But if I say I'm a נזיר עולם, Nazir olam, I
get to take a haircut at the end of the week, right?
It's like, when do I ever get to the מגדל פרע megadel
pera according to this, right? Maybe you say I could say after
the first month, after you got it to the normal stage that
it's considered now wild and unruly, now you can get a trim
on a weekly basis, but doesn't sound like what he's saying. So
it's pretty ironic. All right, let's keep on going. So the גמרא
Gemara says like
this. מאי טעמא דרבי? mai ta'ama de'Rebbi? What's the reasoning of רבי?
Rebbi? We just said the reason because he learns it out from
בתי ערי חומה. batei arei chomah. יליף מבתי ערי חומה. yalif mibatei
arei chomah. He learns it out from the houses of a walled
city. והא רבי הוא דאמר אין ימים פחות משניים. veha Rebbi hu
de'amar ein yamim pachus mishnayim. And רבי Rebbi himself says that there's
another הלכה halacha by בתי ערי חומה. batei arei chomah. It says
ימים תהיה גאולתו, yamim tiheyeh ge'ulaso,
רבי Rebbi reads the word ימים yamim literally, days. And what רבי
Rebbi reads is the following. If I sell you a house in
a walled city, right, the הלכה halacha is that I have a
year to buy it back. Does that mean I can turn around
five minutes later and buy it back? So רבי Rebbi says no.
The sale have to last minimum two days. Okay, so basically, so
that's how he reads it. ימים תהיה גאולתו, yamim tiheyeh ge'ulaso, after
you've waited two days, then you have the rest of the year
to buy it back. Yeah, exactly. So רבי Rebbi reads ימים, yamim,
not meaning a year, meaning literally two days. How can he use
that as the basis to this פסוק pasuk by אבשלום Avshalom to
say it means a year? So the גמרא Gemara says like
this. אין ימים פחות משניים. ein yamim pachus mishnayim. So the גמרא
Gemara says האי גזירה שוה משום כובד גמיר. hai gezeirah shavah mishum
koved gamir. ובשני ימים ליכא כובד. uvishenei yamim leika koved. Okay, one
minute, no. He can't read it literally two days because the whole
idea is to say that the hair got too heavy and that's
explains the context of the allowance. Hair does not get too heavy
after two days, so that cannot be the way he learns it.
Okay, but as long as ימים yamim means plural, ואימא בית שנה.
ve'eima beis shana. How about let's say it means two years? דכתיב
dechitiv ויהי מקץ שנתים ימים. vayehi mikeitz shenasayim yamim.
Here's another פסוק pasuk that has the word ימים yamim and has
it in the context of two years. And it was at the
end of two years of days. So link, oh here it says
ימים, yamim, there it says ימים, yamim, here it means two years,
let's say it's a two year wait. No. דנין ימים שאין עמהם
שנים מימים שאין עמהם שנים. danin yamim she'ein imahem shanim miyamim she'ein
imahem shanim.
The verse by אבשלום Avshalom says ימים לימים, yamim leyammim, it doesn't
mention years. And the verse by בתי ערי חומה batei arei chomah
says ימים תהיה גאולתו. yamim tiheyeh ge'ulaso. And it only mentions a
year in the later פסוק, pasuk, עד מלאת לו שנה תמימה. ad
melos lo shana temimah. But the actual phrase of ימים yamim comes
without the word year. So that's a closer link to the פסוק
pasuk by אבשלום Avshalom rather than linking it to this verb, verse,
where it says שנתים ימים shenasayim yamim where the word ימים yamim
is qualified, you know, through a juxtaposed word of שנתים. shenasayim. So
yes, in this context of שנתים ימים shenasayim yamim it means two
years. But we want to know what the word ימים yamim means
without any qualifier. Okay, that makes a lot of sense, right? If
you have a qualifier, that's one thing. We have the word ימים
yamim appearing by אבשלום Avshalom without a qualifier, we'd like to learn
it from another פסוק pasuk that has ימים yamim without a qualifier,
which is בתי ערי חומה. batei arei chomah. And since... There it
cannot mean two days because that would be absurd by the case
of the נזיר Nazir *Nazir*, we have to say that the ימים
*yamim* there also has the meaning of the next פסוק pasuk *pasuk*,
which is you have until the end of a year. Yes.
It's so interesting cause the medieval פשטנים *pashtanim* all say that ימים
*yamim* means a year. The פשט *pshat* of the term ימים *yamim*
in the תנ"ך *Tanach* is one year.
Interesting. There you go. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says אל
יוכיח זה שיש עמו שנים *Al yochiach zeh sheyeish imo shanim*, so
you can't make any, you can't bring any evidence from a verse
that has a word 'two years' juxtaposed ימים *yamim*. That changes the
meaning of it. So the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says ואימא שלושים יום
*Ve'eima sheloshim yom*, how about thirty days? דכתיב עד חודש ימים *Dechtiv
ad chodesh yamim*, until a month of days? So you see there
ימים *yamim* is used as חודש *chodesh*. The answer's going to be
obvious. There also it's a juxtaposed word that changes what the meaning
of the word ימים *yamim* means. דנין ימים שאין עמהם חודשים מימים
שאין עמהם חודשים *Danin yamim she'ein imahem chodashim miyamim she'ein imahem chodashim*.
No. The verse by אבשלום Avshalom *Avshalom* says ימים *yamim* without a
qualifier, without the word חודשים *chodashim*. The verse by בתי ערי חומה
*batei arei chomah* says ימים *yamim* without a qualifier, without the word
'month'. ואל יוכיח זה שיש עמו חודשים *Ve'al yochiach zeh sheyeish imo
chodashim*, and you can't bring evidence from a verse that has the
word ימים *yamim* qualified by the word month. So therefore with a
qualifier it means something else, but we want to learn what the
word ימים *yamim* means without a qualifier. Okay. And now the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says like this, ואימא מהכא מימים ימימה *Ve'eima meihacha miyamim
yamimah*,
let's learn it from this verse, by the women who would visit
the daughter of יפתח *Yiftach*, right? She was there. It's interesting one
wonders is there some, you know, I mean the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
is just quoting פסוקים pesukim. *pesukim* from all over, but thinking about
נדרים *nedarim* and the power of נדרים *nedarim* and you know and
by שמשון Shimshon, *Shimshon*, the parents, you know, sort of he became
a נדר *neder* not anything he accepted upon himself and יפתח *Yiftach*'s
daughter, you know, whatever happened to her
because of a vow that יפתח *Yiftach* made. Anyway, interesting in the
context of נדרים *nedarim*. But she's there in her like little hut
or wherever she is and before she gets offered to God, these,
you know, the women come and they visit her on a periodic
basis. Okay. And it says in the פסוקים pesukim *pesukim* that they
would come basically four times a year. So if they would come
four times a year and it says מימים ימימה *miyamim yamimah* and
so you divide it, it's an average of three months every time,
so maybe the word ימים *yamim* means every three months? So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says דנין ימים מימים ואין דנין ימים מימימה *Danin
yamim miyamim ve'ein danin yamim miyamimah*.
You learn out the word ימים *yamim* from a simple ימים *yamim*
and not from this פסוק *pasuk* which says ימימה *yamimah*, which is
a slightly different form of the word. So it's not as close
of a match. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says ומאי נפקא מינה
*Umai nafka mina*, who cares when you're making a גזירה שוה *gezeirah
shavah* if the words are exactly the same? והתני דבי רבי ישמעאל
*Veha tana debei Rabbi Yishmael*, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* always loves quoting
this. We have the teaching of רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Yishmael* by the
פסוק *pasuk* about צרעת *tzara'at*, about if there's leprosy in the house,
צרעת *tzara'at* in the house. That one פסוק *pasuk* says ושב הכהן
*Veshav hakohein*, the כהן Kohen *kohein* returns to the house. And another
פסוק *pasuk* says ובא הכהן *Uva hakohein*, the כהן Kohen *kohein* comes
to the house. And what we do is we make a גזירה
שוה *gezeirah shavah* and we say זו היא שיבה זו היא ביאה
*Zo hi shivah zo hi biah*, returning to the house, coming to
the house, it's the same point. You came to the house. So
therefore we learn what it says from one of those sections to
the other because we say the words connect, they're essentially the same
point. So that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says could be evidence that
by גזירה שוה *gezeirah shavah* it doesn't have to be the exact
same word. As long as the sense is the same, the actual
word itself doesn't have to be identical. Okay, so this is always
what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* throws this in to raise the question
of whether a גזירה שוה *gezeirah shavah* has to be a precise
matching of words. And the answer is always the same, one minute,
the answer is הני מילי היכא דליכא דדמי ליה *Hani mili heicha
deleika dedami leih*. That's if we have no other choice. If you
have no closer, if you have no closer match you can, גזירה
שוה *gezeirah shavah* will tolerate a link of meaning even if it's
not a link of the exact same words. אבל היכא דאיכא דדמי
ליה *Aval heicha de'ika dedami leih*, but if there's a closer match,
מדדמי ליה ילפינן *midedami leih yalpinan*, a גזירה שוה *gezeirah shavah* only
you know forces you to do the best closest match to that
word in terms of the word itself, not just its meaning. So
therefore we're not going to learn from יפתח *Yiftach* where it says
ימים ימימה *yamim yamimah*, which is four times a year. We're going
to learn from בתי ערי חומה *batei arei chomah* that says ימים
*yamim*, which is once a year. ואיכא דאמרי *Ve'ika de'amri*, and one
last explanation why we're not going to learn from יפתח *Yiftach*, is
מנא ידעה דכל תלתא ירחי חד זימנא *Mena yade'ah dechol tlata yarchi
chad zimna*? Who tells you just because they visited four times a
year, it meant they did it at a perfect spacing? Three months
at a time? דילמא ארבע זימני בשתא *Dilma arba zimnei beshata*, four
times a year, but they were a little like, you know, irregular
in terms of how frequently they would visit within that space. ארבע
ירחי חד זימנא *Arba yarchi chad zimna*, first maybe they'd first have
a gap of four months, תרי ירחי בחד זימנא *trei yarchi bechad
zimna*, then a gap of two months and so on and so
forth. So just because it was four times a year, you can't
prove that it was every three months. And since therefore we don't
know how frequent that is, you can't learn from יפתח *Yiftach* any
sense of any periodic standard length. That's why you don't learn from
יפתח *Yiftach*. So bottom line is אבשלום Avshalom *Avshalom* is being understood
to be a נזיר Nazir. *Nazir*. He would go and he would
satisfy his vows. That shows us a... And understood to mean that
he would bring his קרבנות korbanos. *Korbanot* that would let him trim
his hair, and he would do this periodically, מימים לימים *Miyamim l'yamim*,
which we're understanding to mean on a yearly basis and that's where
רבי *Rabbi* gets the idea that a נזיר עולם Nazir Olam, *Nazir
Olam* can trim his hair on a yearly basis if he brings
a קרבן korban, *Korban*. Yes?
What do you think about this? The structure of the סוגיא *Sugya*
is forcing me to learn the ברייתא *Braita* of רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi
Yishmael* who is very concerned with traditions of hermeneutics to read that
ברייתא *Braita* as if he's talking about a גזירה שוה *Gezeira Shavah*
in context. Does that ברייתא *Braita* talk about a גזירה שוה *Gezeira
Shavah*? It's not a גזירה שוה *Gezeira Shavah* to say that these
two different words are synonyms.
Okay, so you are right that I mean there's two things. Number
one is רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Yishmael* himself is דברה תורה Torah כלשון
בני אדם *Dibra Torah k'lashon b'nei adam* so he more goes anyway
in terms of meaning than in terms of the
precise morphology or the
precise letter perfect aspect of the word. Number two is if he's
necessarily using the גזירה שוה *Gezeira Shavah* modality. That's a bigger question
also whether what גזירה שוה *Gezeira Shavah* originally meant. There's actually an
early משנה Mishnah. *Mishna* about בית הלל ובית שמאי *Beit Hillel u'Beit
Shammai*, it might even be שמאי והלל *Shammai v'Hillel* that they say
when they're comparing two rabbinic laws—I forget what it was, I think
one was
עירוב תחומין *Eiruv Techumin*
case. Anyway, it was two rabbinic laws and they say גזירה שוה
*Gezeira Shavah*! Look, you can make a comparison between the two. So
גזירה שוה *Gezeira Shavah* in its earliest form might not have meant
this sort of technical magic of you link two words and you
get to transfer the ideas. It might have initially meant that these
two concepts are analogous and comparable and therefore you can—you know, might
have been more of a logical point than of a formal thing
that allows you to just automatically transfer all of the laws from
one to the other. Anyway, for another זמן *Zman*, but yes, so
thank you, that's a good point. So now let's go on. The
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this, so that's רבי *Rabbi*. רבי נהוראי
אומר *Rabbi Nehorai omer*, רבי נהוראי *Rabbi Nehorai* says, מגלח megaleach אחת
לשלשים יום *Megalaiach achat l'shloshim yom*, once every thirty days. Okay, where
do you get that from? מאי טעמא *Mai ta'ama*, where do you
get what's the reason, what's behind that? גבי כהנים *Gabei kohanim*, because
of the כהנים *Kohanim*. משום דאיכא כובד *Mishum d'ika koved*, כהנים *Kohanim*
cannot let their hair be גדל פרע pera *Gadel pera*, grow wild
and that's because after thirty days it's considered to be growing wild.
הכא נמי איכא כובד *Hacha nami ika koved*, here too it's considered
to be too weighty. Now of course תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* points out
this is ironic because the only way we know כהנים *Kohanim* when
it says it has to be—that they can't allow their hair to
be גדל פרע pera. *Gadel pera*—means more than thirty days is from—any
guesses? Where do you think we would learn that the definition of
hair growing wild for a כהן *Kohen* is more than thirty days?
From a נזיר Nazir. *Nazir*. A standard נזירות neziros. *Nezirut* is thirty
days. We're going to see about that in the next משנה Mishnah.
*Mishna*. And the נזירות Nezirus *Nezirut* when his hair is described as
that it has to be גדל פרע pera *Gadel pera*, it has
to be wild and unruly. So we see from a נזיר Nazir
*Nazir* that thirty days' growth defines the hair to be that way.
A כהן *Kohen* is not allowed to let his hair be גדל
פרע pera. *Gadel pera*, so for a נזיר Nazir *Nazir*—so that means
thirty days. So that's how we get to a כהן *Kohen*. So
now we're saying how do you know that a נזיר עולם Nazir
Olam, *Nazir Olam* gets to trim his hair after thirty days? Oh,
because for כהנים *Kohanim* that's considered to be wild growth. That's a
little funny how it went this way, right? Why didn't you just
say from a normal נזיר Nazir, *Nazir* you see that's wild growth?
So תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* says, well maybe we'd rather not learn נזיר
עולם Nazir Olam *Nazir Olam* from נזיר Nazir, שעה *Nazir Sha'ah*, maybe
כהנים *Kohanim* is a more neutral basis. But it's very funny because
it's all coming from the idea that we have by a נזיר
Nazir, *Nazir* that more than thirty days is a wild growth. Okay,
again it's pretty funny because if you think about it, it's like
what are we saying? I get that after thirty—here's basically my question.
When a נזיר עולם Nazir Olam *Nazir Olam* gets his trim, does
the hair have to—can it get back to the pre-thirty day length?
Right? Can a נזיר עולם Nazir Olam. *Nazir Olam*'s hair be not
גדל פרע pera *Gadel pera*? Here I am, I'm going through my
life as a נזיר nazir *Nazir*, but my hair always looks perfect
because every
thirty-one days—maybe there's one day where it gets unruly, day thirty-one—and then
I get a nice little trim and it looks totally acceptable so
for another thirty days it looks totally fine, right? So it's interesting
that I would think that as a נזיר עולם nazir olam, *Nazir
Olam* I'm allowed to get it trimmed but it still has to
remain at the status of פרע pera. *Pera*. It still has to
remain, you know, larger than it would be after thirty days. If
I'm getting it trimmed every thirty days, then it's sort of always
getting to be under the פרע pera *Pera* state, so it's very
strange. Yes.
Go ahead.
Is it possible that פרע pera *Pera* just means—as we saw in
the last סוגיא *Sugya*—it actually just means beautiful, that a כהן *Kohen*
shouldn't have his hair be too long and beautiful and then in
context of the third time that פרע pera *Pera* is used right
in the sequence of the סוטה *Sotah*, that the idea of having
a woman's hair uncovered because of פרע pera *Pera*, beauty?
I don't think no—I mean first of all logically that wouldn't make
sense. Why I mean you're taking the point I made that is
the נזיר nazir *Nazir*'s hair sometimes seen as beautiful in these פסוקים
pesukim, *Pesukim*, but it's very clear from the context like it says
after חטא העגל *Cheit Ha'eigel*, כי פרעו אהרן *Ki fera'o Aharon*, כי
פרוע הוא *Ki farua hu*, כי פרעו אהרן *Ki fera'o Aharon*, ופרע
ראש האשה *U'fara rosh ha'isha*, why would we be trying to make
the סוטה *Sotah* whose whole ritual there is about, you know, sort
of about degrading? Why would we be—so it doesn't— It doesn't fit
in the context here.
I would think I was
thinking unless there's the נזיר nazir, עולם and he gets a little
trim every thirty days. Right. The פרע pera. aspect is a lifelong
status. No he's always cutting it a little bit.
So that's my question. That's what I'm asking. How much is he
cutting it?
There's my question, right?
Here's the נזיר nazir עולם, right? This is his hair after thirty
days. You like that? Okay. That's his hair—no that's his hair twenty-nine
days. That's not yet פרע. Now his hair is like this. Now
he's thirty days it's פרע and now he's able to get a
trim. Can he get this? Or no he's only allowed to do
that. But even if he does that he's back down to the
twenty-nine day status, not considered a פרע. Another twenty-nine days later. So
he's only allowed to get after thirty days, he's only allowed to
get the thing that's after thirty days. He has to remain—that's what
I'm asking. Does he have to keep the פרע status of his
hair? Okay. The גמרא's Gemara not clear about that.
Also the embedding of the כהן here is because the נזיר nazir,
and כהן are constantly—right.
Right it is true, but it's still funny that we're importing something
that we eventually that we originally got from נזיר. nazir All right
let's continue. So it says, okay, רבי יוסי אומר מגלח מערב שבת
לערב שבת, Rabbi Yose omer megalayeach m'erev Shabbos l'erev Shabbos, every Friday.
מאי קסבר? Mai kasavar? Says the גמרא, Gemara so it's very nice.
First of all, again, that really raises the question. Here's a guy,
the נזיר nazir, עולם, his hair always looks perfect. He gets a
weekly haircut. It's so—that's totally—I mean I can't begin to understand that,
how you can be a נזיר nazir, עולם and have your hair
always be—get a weekly haircut. Anyways the גמרא Gemara says
unless he already has his פרע. He has his hair, and
it's—so that's what I was ask—right, so that's unless that's it. You
first have to grow the פרע and then every week you get
to trim it again to like the pre—to the just you know
to the pre-פרע status or to just lessen it.
I would also like to interject on a personal note. Let's say
theoretically I became a נזיר.
Nazir I
think I would be פרע challenged.
Thank you very much.
Yes, it's leveling the playing field a little bit.
All right. All right, thank you. Okay, so it says like this.
No, נזיר Nazir. עולם is a permanent נזירות.
Nezirus Right, but I'm saying that maybe if since you're becoming a
נזיר Nazir, forever that there's like one area that you could be
sort of like lax.
Yeah, but the laxity would seem to be to allow you to
violate, as it were, or the prohibition of cutting the hair. One
would still think that the state, state of being פרע should be
maintained, right? I understand, that's what would emerge, is that we're actually
making it actually not just that the act of cutting is permissible,
but the actual state of being a נזיר Nazir, looks different, looks
more acceptable for him, which is strange. It's very strange. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says like this. מאי איכא ביניה? Mai ika beinei?
So we know that he learned it out because he assumes that
אבשלום Avshalom must have done it on a weekly basis. So the
גמרא Gemara says, מאי איכא ביניה ושאר אחיו? Mai ika beinei v'sha'ar
echav? So then how is אבשלום different than any other of his
brothers, the other princes? They're all also getting a haircut on a
weekly basis. So you know real—so it doesn't say that his hair
is in פרע. That's my question. It's just saying his hair is
completely like everybody else's. So the גמרא Gemara says, what's the difference?
יום טוב שחל להיות באמצע שבת. Yom Tov shechal lihayos b'emtza Shabbas.
Oh, a difference would be if you have a יום טוב Yom
Tov in the middle of the week. דאחוהי מגלחין, D'echav megalchin, other
of his brothers of course would get a haircut because of—you know
כבוד יום טוב, Kavod Yom Tov, שמחת יום טוב. Simchas Yom Tov.
איהו לא מגלח, Ihu lo megalach, he wouldn't be able to get
a haircut in the middle of the week. So that would be
a case a time where he would look a little different than
his brothers. אי נמי אור לגלוחי מצפרא דמעלי שבתא. I nami ur
l'giluychi mitzafra d'ma'alei Shabata.
How about getting it, you know Friday morning? אחוהי מערב שבתא אחוהי
מגלחין, Echav m'erev Shabta echav megalchin,
they could get their haircut already Friday morning. איהו, Ihu, since he
has this idea of the prohibition of a נזיר, Nazir he'd have
to wait until the last minute. לא מגלח עד פניא, Lo megalach
ad panya, until the evening, until like right before sunset. And תוספות
by the way also points out, maybe this also includes the idea
that he couldn't bring—get a haircut unless he brought his קרבנות. korbanos.
Okay? And he says maybe that's what it means until the evening.
You first got to bring your קרבנות. korbanos But what it's really
asking is not the קרבנות korbanos. question. It's like, how does he
look different in his hair than his brothers? All right, so very
interesting range of opinions here. Now the גמרא Gemara says just a
question, הני ארבעים שנה מאי עבידתייהו? Hanei arbayim shana mai avidteihu? Why—what
do you mean he did it after forty years? And the implicitly
he did his rebellion. And the implicit question is is that דוד
Dovid was only king for thirty-seven years. So it can't mean forty
years from the beginning of דוד's Dovid kingship. So the גמרא gemara
says, רב נהוראי אומר משום רבי יהושע לקץ מ"ם שנה ששאלו להם
מלך. Rav Nehorai omer mishum Rabbi Yehoshua l'ketz mem shana she'sha'alu lahem
melech. It's forty years counting back to the time when בני ישראל
Bnei Yisrael asked for a king from שמואל. Shmuel. And the analogy
that one of the מפרשים Meforshim say is they sort of rebelled
against the divine kingship by wanting an earthly king, which clearly is
what שמואל Shmuel talks about when he is very offended by their
request. And so here now forty years later, אבשלום is rebelling against
his father's kingship. Okay, תנא, Tana, we taught, אותה שנה ששאלו להם
מלך היא שנת עשר לשמואל הרמתי. Osa shana she'sha'alu lahem melech hi
shenas eser l'Shmuel HaRamasi.
The year that they asked for a king was the tenth year
of the career of שמואל, Shmuel, and that is long explanations about
how the גמרא—how that they do—they have to say that in order
to explain how all the math works out in terms of all
the chronology. and all the dates. Yes.
Did you say anything about רב— Rav is there anything for you
to say about רב נהוראי? Rav Nehorai? You know, was he a
very late Amoraic גאון? Gaon?
No, he's— he's Tannaic. I don't— I mean, I know— yeah, I
mean I know he's— תנא? Tanna? Yeah, I don't know the exact
dates, but he's a standard תנא. Tanna. Okay, I know it's a
funny name. Alright, let's take a look. Next משנה. Mishnah סתם נזירות
שלשים יום. Stam Nezirus shloshim yom.
Standard נזירות Nezirus is 30 days. Very simple משנה. Mishnah. Question of
where we get this from, but it means if somebody does not,
you know, סתם, satam, סתם stam is also the difference of מפורש,
m'forash, מפרש, m'faresh, meaning you're not explicating. You just say I'm a
נזיר, Nazir. you don't say how long. Unexplicated נזירות nezirut. is 30
days. Standard unexplicated 30 days. Okay, so in— so after 30 days
you get to bring your קרבנות. korbanos. Now we're back to the
world of normal נזיר, Nazir, not just שמשון, נזיר שמשון, Nazir Shimshon,
נזיר Nazir עולם. Okay, so גמרא says like this: מני מילי? Mani
milei? How do I know that? That a נזירות nezirus is assumed
to be 30 days? So אמר רב מתנא אמר קרא, Amar Rav
Masna amar kra, the verse says: קדוש יהיה, Kadosh yihiyeh, holy will
be the growing of his hair, גדל פרע שער ראשו. gadel pera
se'ar rosho. יהיה בגימטריא תלתין הוו. Yihiyeh be-gematria tlasin havu. So do
the math, right? יהיה yihiyeh in גימטריא, gematria, יוד yud and a
יוד yud and two ה heis is 30. Alright, so that's one.
Always interesting when גימטריא gematria plays a role in הלכה. Halacha. But
בר פדא אמר— Bar Pada amar obviously what it seems clear sometimes
also when you just have like five different, you know, ways of
learning out the same הלכה, Halacha, it seems very clear that they
basically had a tradition, and we have this tradition, now we have
to figure out how we're going to connect it back to the
פסוקים. pesukim Okay, which is by the way an interesting whole debate
in the ראשונים Rishonim and in the academics in general about all
the דרשות drashot of חז"ל. Chazal. Do we assume that חז"ל Chazal
really derived the laws from their דרשות, drashot, they really didn't know
and they said let's look at the פסוקים pesukim and figure out
what the laws are? Or did they start with traditions about what
the laws were and they just said, "Well, we have to connect
it back to the פסוקים, pesukim let's find a way to connect
it back." So, you know, and the most obvious answer to that
is yes and yes. Like sometimes they did one and sometimes they
did the other. And, you know, when everybody sort of assumes a
law and nobody debates that the law is true, but everybody is
throwing out different פסוקים pesukim about how to learn it, that presumably
they started with the tradition and now they're just trying to link
it back. And when there's actually more of a debate of the
law and you have like one or two, you know, opinions— well
let's say two opinions, not five different פסוקים being thrown out— then
it makes more sense they actually are trying to derive the law
and therefore, you know, you do— you have actually different opinions. Okay,
so here it seems like we started with the idea of 30
days and now we're trying to link it back. בר פדא אמר
כנגד נזיר נזרו האמורים בתורה ל' חסר אחת. Bar Pada amar k'neged
nazir neziru ha'amurim ba'torah lamed chasar achas.
So בר פדא Bar Pada says go count the times it says
in the תורה Torah, the word נזיר Nazir or נזרו, neziru, and
you'll find out that it will be 29 times. Now, we were—
we were going for 30. So here's the interesting irony: actually, if
you go and count the times it says נזיר Nazir, and נזרו
neziru in the תורה, Torah it is 30! Alright?
So, which is great! So he says, "Well, one of them you
had to say it, you had to introduce the concept." You know,
or— or the ראשונים Rishonim say, or the ראשונים Rishonim say because
when it says כי נזר אלוהיו על ראשו, ki nezer elohav al
rosho, נזר nezer in that פסוק means the crown, it doesn't mean
the נזירות. nezirus? So somehow, although there were 30, he only counted
29 of them. And that's going to lead to the discussion we're
about to go into, which is according to בר פדא, Bar Pada,
סתם נזירות stam nezirus really is 29 days, not 30, except if
I go— if I have to go to the end of day
29 and I only get to end it when I bring my
קרבן, korban and I can't bring my קרבן korban at night, I'm
going to wind up bringing my קרבן korban. on day 30. But
בר פדא Bar Pada says in principle it's 29 days, it's just
you have to wait till day 30 to bring your קרבן. korban,
So it's very interesting, and he does it— the פסוקים say 30
times נזיר, nazir but he counts only 29 of them. What?
And this is סתם. stam.
And this is סתם, stam, סתם נזירות. stam nezirus. This is unexplicated.
Right? What— I—
what?
No, it's just like ironic.
Why is it ironic?
Because it's סתם stam and then it goes into a גימטריא. gematria.
No, but that's the point. Meaning the— I don't understand your point
about סתם stam and גימטריא. gematria. Meaning, if somebody says I'm a
נזיר nazir without explicating, what should we assume when the תורה Torah
describes a נזיר, nazir is the תורה Torah, assuming about what the
duration is? So that's the question. Oh, it says the word נזיר
nazir 30 times in the תורה, Torah it's assuming the duration is
30 days. It's bizarre because it's sort of this counting thing that's
going on, but not because of the סתם stam element.
Meaning I understand the סתם stam as just because of the one—
one time of נזיר, nazir but you're saying it's from all the
30 times and that's—
No, the גמרא— the תורה Torah says somebody is a נזיר, nazir.
here's what he does, and when he finishes his נזירות nezirut. he
brings his קרבנות. korbanot The תורה Torah never tells you when does
he finish his נזירות? nezirut? Right? The תורה Torah somehow assumes there's
an understood period of נזירות. nezirut, Okay? So, if you don't say
otherwise, maybe you can say I'm going to do it for a
year, for five years, but if you don't say otherwise, what's the
assumed, the סתם stam period of נזירות? nezirut. And the answer is
30 days. How do you know that? So now we have to—
okay, but the same way we use all types of rabbinic tools,
you know, hermeneutic tools to get— to get weird. things, but that's
what we're saying, the Torah's describing this סתם stam period and we're
going to learn the פסוקים and say you get thirty out of
it. Okay, thirty days. So that's what we get, למ"ד חסר אחת.
lamed chasar achat. רב מתנא נמי נילף מנזיר נזרא. Rav Matna nami
neilef miNazir Nizra.
So, for Rav Matna, why don't you count by the way I
should also say an interesting other place where it says where the
idea of חסר אחת chasar achat is and a similar type of
gematria is מלאכות. melachot. How do you know the idea of thirty-nine
מלאכות? melachot? So one answer is because every time it says the
word מלאכה, melacha, מלאכתו, melachto, מלאכת melechet whatever in the Torah, you
get it to thirty-nine. Of course the other problem is really you
get it to more like fifty-three or so.
So the ראשונים rishonim have to do a really hard job trimming
it down to explain how the גמרא got to thirty-nine. Anyway, okay,
so now you have Bar Pada counting twenty-nine times. So the גמרא
says ורב מתנא נמי נילף מנזיר נזרא, VeRav Matna nami neilef miNazir
Nizra, rather than going to your גמטריא, gematria, why not learn out
from נזיר נזרא? Nazir Nizra? אמר
לך, Amar lach, he'll say to you, no, ההוא לדרשה. hahu ledrasha.
Every time it says an extra word נזיר nazir. in the Torah,
I'm going to teach me something new about the laws of נזיר.
nazir, For example, like we learned yesterday, מיין ושכר יזיר, miyayin veshechar
yazir, he should you know remove himself from wine and intoxicating liquid.
So what does that extra יזיר yazir tell you? לאסור יין מצוה
כיין רשות, le'esor yayin mitzvah keyayin reshut, even mitzvah wine he can't
drink like we discussed a day or two ago. כי יפלי לנדור
נדר נזיר, Ki yafuli lindor neder Nazir, if a person enunciates to
take a vow of נזירות, nezirut להזיר לה'. lehazir l'Hashem. So what
does that doubling language of נזיר להזיר Nazir lehazir tell you? מלמד
שנזירות חלה על נזירות, melamed she'nezirut chala al nezirut, a person can
experience a double נזירות. nezirut And what it means is if I
say basically, if I eat this loaf of bread I'll be a
נזיר, nazir, and then I say and if I eat like I
don't know you know this loaf of bread I'll be a נזיר,
nazir and I put both the loaves of bread in my mouth
at the same time, so we would say that actually a double
נזירות nezirut would mean I have one נזירות nezirut took effect and
the other is hovering and when I finish one, the other one
kicks in. Okay, so and that idea that we can have one
waiting and hovering in abeyance is learned out from this word נזיר
להזיר. Nazir lehazir. So basically he says I can't count every single
time it says the word נזיר because I need those words to
tell me הלכה, halacha, extra הלכות halachot about a נזיר. So the
גמרא says ובר פדא אמר לך, uvar Pada amar lach, Bar Pada
would say back to you, לית חד מנהון דלאו לדרשה. leit chad
min'hon d'lav ledrasha.
Look, they're not going to come up with twenty-nine דרשות drashot about
a נזיר, okay? So one of those words minimally is superfluous, is
not going to teach you a דרשה. drasha. Once that's true, אלא
מדאהו למניינא, ela mide'hahu leminyana, since one of those words is extra
and which must, so therefore its only purpose would be to tell
you how to count towards the number of days, כלהו נמי למניינא,
kulhu nami leminyana, they're all able to be counted towards to tell
you the number of days. Yes you use those extra words for
a דרשה, drasha, but some of the words can't be used for
a דרשה, drasha, and that's telling you that all the presence of
the word נזיר is to tell you more than just a specific
הלכה, halacha, they're actually supposed to count up the occurrences and that's
supposed to tell you something as well. All right, are you convinced
Rabbi Dov? Okay, fine, סתם stam is סתם. stam. תנן, Tnan, this
okay,
now we're going to fine, put aside the דרשות. drashot. We actually
have a more interesting debate of whether נזירות neziros, is really thirty
days or is it really twenty-nine days but you just can't bring
your קרבנות korbanot until day thirty. Let's see what some of the
different differences might be. תנן, Tnan, סתם נזירות שלשים יום. Stam nezirut
sheloshim yom.
סתם נזירות Stam nezirut is thirty days. בשלמא לרב מתנא ניחא. Bishlama
leRav Matna nicha. For Rav Matna it's fine, that's what he says,
he says thirty. אלא לבר פדא קשיא. Ela leVar Pada kashya. For
Bar Pada it's a problem, he said twenty-nine. אמר לך בר פדא,
Amar lach Bar Pada, Bar Pada will tell you no, אידי ואידי
יום שלשים דמגלח ומייתי קרבנותיו נמי. idi ve'idi yom sheloshim d'megaleach umeiti
korbanotav nami. No because you have to wait until day thirty in
order to shave and to bring your קרבנות korbanos and only then
are you allowed to be your נזיר period stop, once you bring
your קרבן, korban משום הכי תני שלשים. mishum hachi tani sheloshim. It
won't end until day thirty. In principle the duration is twenty-nine days,
but you won't be able to do the thing to end it
until day thirty. Okay, let's try again. תנן, Tnan, מי שאמר הריני
נזיר. Mi she'amar hareini Nazir. We're going to come up to a
משנה mishnah pretty soon. Somebody says I'm a נזיר, מגלח יום שלשים
ואחד. megaleach yom sheloshim ve'echad.
He has to wait until thirty-one. Why would he have to wait
until thirty-one? Well, if you say נזירות nezirus is thirty days, so
then you could say you have to wait till the at the
end of thirty days you're done and you bring your קרבן korban
on day thirty-one. But if it's twenty-nine days we just said that
even if you wait the full twenty-nine, you bring your קרבן korban
on day thirty. So let's take a look. מי שאמר הריני נזיר
מגלח יום שלשים ואחד. Mi she'amar hareini Nazir megaleach yom sheloshim ve'echad.
בשלמא לרב מתנא ניחא. Bishlama leRav Matna nicha. For Rav
Matna it's good, it's a thirty-day duration and you bring your קרבן
korban on day thirty-one. אלא לבר פדא קשיא. Ela leVar Pada kashya.
For Bar Pada it's difficult because he should be able to bring
his קרבן korban. on day thirty. אמר לך בר פדא, Amar lach
Bar Pada, אימא סיפא. eima seifa. Look, look at the end of
that משנה. mishnah אם גילח ביום שלשים יצא. Im gilach beyom sheloshim
yatza. בדיעבד Bedi'avad it works on day thirty. So
I can explain why it בדיעבד bedi'avad works on day thirty because
for me it was a twenty-nine day and day thirty you can
end it. But according to who is it, Rav Matna? Was it
Rav Matna? Yeah, according to Rav Matna,
how should it ever work בדיעבד bedi'avad on day thirty? You needed
a thirty-day duration. And then you would bring your קרבנות korbanos on
day 31. אלא סיפא מסייעי ליה. Ella seifa mesaye'ei leh.
Fine, the end of it seems to prove he's right that day
30 if you bring your קרבנות korbanos. on day 30 it means
it only lasted 29 days. How do we explain why לכתחילה lechatchila
you have to wait till day 31? רישא נעשה כאומר שלמים Reisha
na'aseh ke'omer shleimim
because I'm afraid that let's say somebody says full days. Now of
course full days wouldn't matter. You're already waiting 29 full days and
you're bringing them on day 30. So תוספות says it doesn't really
mean somebody will say שלמים, shleimim, somebody will say I'm a נזיר
for שלשים יום. shloshim yom. Okay, now of course why would somebody
say that? So it seems clear that even if סתם נזירות stam
nezirus is 29 days for בר פדא, Bar Padda, the difference between
29 days and a month in your like mindset, you know, you
think it's gonna last for a month. You don't think 29 days
or whatever. So he's saying it's true, if you said nothing, 29
days, bring it on day 30. But it's quite likely that somebody
will say I'm going to be a נזיר for a month because
it's pretty close in their mind one or the other. And in
that case they'd have to wait till day 31. So therefore I'm
going to say that everybody should wait till day 31 just so
it doesn't get confused. Okay, but in principle, you know, if you
say I'm a סתם נזיר, stam nazir, of course you can even
in principle לכתחילה lechatchila bring it on day 30. But because of
confusion, I'll tell people to wait till day 31. That's how בר
פדא Bar Padda explains לכתחילה lechatchila day 31, בדיעבד bedieved day 30.
Now let's figure out רב מתנה Rav Masna because for him you
understand why day 31, but how do you get away בדיעבד bedieved
with doing it on day 30? So the גמרא says like this,
ולרב מתנה קשיא סיפא, Ulerav Masna kashya seifa, what does רב מתנה
Rav Masna deal with the end? How does he explain בדיעבד bedieved
you can do it on day 30? קסבר מקצת היום ככולו. Kasavar
miktzas hayom kekulo.
Yes, the same way as we know perfect example of this is
אבילות. aveilus. אבילות Aveilus is seven days, but a person gets up
at the beginning of day seven. Right, there's an idea that part
of a day counts as a full day. Okay, also a הלכה
halacha that applies in the תורה for let's say a woman who
is a זבה zava who counts seven days of non-bleeding and according
to the הלכה halacha she can go to the מקוה mikveh actually
in the beginning of the seventh day. We say מקצת היום ככולו.
miktzas hayom kekulo. Okay, not true by a נדה. niddah. נדה Niddah
has to wait till the end of the seventh day. Any interesting
cases when do we say מקצת היום, miktzas hayom, when don't we?
But anyway, what it's saying here is that yes, it is in
principle 30 day duration, but you don't have to wait till the
end of day 30 and bring it on day 31. As long
as you started day 30, that's good enough and now you can
bring your קרבנות. korbanos But since that relies on the trick of
מקצת היום ככולו, miktzas hayom kekulo, we'd rather you wait till day
31. But בדיעבד bedieved you brought it on day 30, that also
counts. Now that's interesting. Normally we don't have a לכתחילה lechatchila idea
about מקצת היום ככולו. miktzas hayom kekulo. We normally don't say, oh,
although best to do the whole seven days, but if you need
to get up at the beginning of the seventh day, that's what
we don't say. We say you did the beginning of seven, you're
done. Okay, you know, so it's interesting sometimes when do we want
you to not rely on מקצת היום ככולו miktzas hayom kekulo when
we do. But that's what רב מתנה Rav Masna is saying is,
yes, it's 30 days, but you can בדיעבד bedieved at least you
can do it at the beginning of day 30, מקצת היום ככולו,
miktzas hayom kekulo, part of the day is like the whole day.
So how does this affect if there are consecutive נזירות, nezirut 30
and another?
Excellent, we're about to get to that. Okay, so תנן. tnan. Now
let's look at another related משנה mishnah here that is basically going
to be the same thing except back to back. הריני נזיר שלשים
יום. Hareini nazir shloshim yom. I am a נזיר for 30 days.
אם גילח יום שלשים לא יצא. Im gileach yom shloshim lo yatza.
So if you, well, if you did it on day 30 you're
not יוצא. yotza. So clearly here, if you say שלשים יום, shloshim
yom, it means full 30 days. You don't say מקצת היום ככולו.
miktzas hayom kekulo. How does that work according to anybody, right? So
the גמרא says, well, actually בר פדא Bar Padda might not hold
of מקצת היום ככולו. miktzas hayom kekulo. Right, but because בר פדא
Bar Padda needs full days, full 29 days. But how does it
work for רב מתנה? Rav Masna? Why don't you say מקצת היום?
miktzas hayom? So it says the גמרא says באומר שלמים. Be'omer shleimim.
No, no, no, you said 30 full days, okay, and therefore that's
why it doesn't work because if you're saying 30 full days then
you can no longer use מקצת היום ככולו. miktzas hayom kekulo. Fine.
תנן, Tnan, let's go back to a משנה mishnah. like the first
one we quoted. מי שנזר ב' נזיריות. Mi shenazar shetei neziriyos.
Somebody said I will be a נזיר and I'll be a נזיר
after the first one is done. מגלח את הראשונה יום ל"א. Megaleach
es harishonah yom lamed aleph.
So he shaves the first one after day 31 והשנייה ליום ס"א
vehasheniyah leyom samech aleph
and the second after day 61. So just to show you, because
sometimes you know sometimes counting or whatever you get lost like you
count the first number and not the first number whatever anyway. So
if you go from day 1 to 31, right? So this is,
right, this was your
30, so so this was your 30 full days and then you
bring your קרבנות korbanos, here. So that's not assuming מקצת היום ככולו
miktzas hayom kekulo because לכתחילה lechatchila you're not supposed to assume מקצת
היום ככולו. miktzas hayom kekulo. Okay, so 31 days is then when
you shave. And then you go to day 61. Now how does
that work? Because on day 31 when you brought your קרבנות, okay,
you ended your נזירות nezirut, in the middle of the day and
then your second one started in the middle of the day. So
day 31 also became for the second נזירות nezirut, day 1. So
day 61 becomes day 31. Okay, so all it's basically saying is
that you wait till day 31, but the first day 31 ends
one and begins the other. Okay, that's what that's saying.
I
just have to clarify something. Rabbi you said it was really simple
but just on a regular נזירות, nezirut. so my 30 days are
over. Yeah. Independent of this מחלוקת. machloket. Right. I don't bring my
קרבן. korban Right.
You're still a נזיר. Full נזיר. Yeah. Yeah. Exactly.
That's why Rav Kook's student, the נזיר, even if he did not
even if he was not a נזיר עולם, in effect was not
able to end his נזירות, nezirut. right, because there was no קרבן
korban he could bring.
Right. So בזמן הזה, bizman hazeh, someone becomes a נזיר, it's a
נזיר for life.
Yep. Okay. So now the משנה mishnah says: מי שנזר שתי נזירות
מגלח את הראשונה יום שלושים ואחד והשנייה ליום שישים ואחד. mi shenazar
shtei nezirut megaleach et harishona yom shloshim ve'echad vehashniya leyom shishim ve'echad.
בשלמא לרב מתנה ניחא. bishlama leRav Matna nicha.
Now we're basically asking the exact same questions we asked before and
we're going to give the same answers. בשלמא לרב מתנה ניחא bishlama
leRav Matna nicha for Rav Matna that makes sense. You wait till
day 31 because it's a 30-day נזירות. nezirut. אלא לבר פדא קשיא.
ela leBar Pada kashya. For Bar Pada it's difficult. Why are you
waiting till day 31? Wait till day 30 since it's a 29-day
נזירות. nezirut. אמר לך בר פדא. amar lach Bar Pada. So Bar
Pada says, אימא סיפא, eima seifa, let's look at the end of
the משנה. ואם גילח את הראשונה ליום שלושים מגלח את השנייה ליום
שישים. ve'im gilach et harishona leyom shloshim megaleach et hashniya leyom shishim.
So it says let's say though, instead of doing day 31, you
went ahead and you did your thing, you brought your קרבן and
you did your thing on day 30, which we said works, right?
It either works for מקצת היום ככולו mikzat hayom kekulo or it
works because it was only a 29-day נזירות. nezirut. So you did
it on day 30. So day 30 becomes your now new day
1. Okay, so what would be... so in order to get to
this day 31 so you're always supposed to לכתחילה lechatchila do it
on 31, we're going to add 30 to this 30, which would
get us day 60. I mean we add 30 because that would
get us day 31, right? So then 30 will become day 60,
right? So the first one you did for 30 days and the
second one you did for 31 and you're מגלח on day 60.
So that's what it says. אימא סיפא... eima seifa... ואם גילח את
הראשונה ליום שלושים, ve'im gilach et harishona leyom shloshim, if you did
the first one on day 30, מגלח את השנייה ליום שישים. megaleach
et hashniya leyom shishim. The second one you still לכתחילה lechatchila do
the 31 days and you do it on day 60. So the
גמרא says so anyway, but the bottom line is it allows for
it to end on day 30 בדיעבד. bedi'avad.
So that works for me. אלא סיפא מסייע ליה. ela seifa mesaya
leh. That works for me because I will say you can do
it on day 30. So רישא, reisha, what? How do I explain
why לכתחילה lechatchila you're supposed to wait till day
31? באומר שלמים. be'omer shelemim. Again, you said full, which really he
doesn't mean full, it's borrowing the other language of שלמים. shelemim. It
really means you said I'm going to do a 30-day נזירות. nezirut
And therefore that's when we'd wait, make you wait till 61. Or
we're afraid of cases where you're going to say I'll do a
full 30-day נזירות. nezirut. And therefore לכתחילה lechatchila we ask everybody to
do it on day 31. But in principle normal נזירות nezirut can
be on day 30 because it was 29 days and day 30
is the following day. So that's exactly what he said before. ולרב
מתנה קשיא סיפא. ulerav matna kashya seifa. According to Rav Matna, back
to the same question we asked before, why בדיעבד bedi'avad does it
work on day 30? Your 30 days aren't up on day 30.
So אמר לך רב מתנה, amar lach Rav Matna, he'll say to
you, כדתני סיפא יום שלושים עולה לכאן ולכאן, kedtani seifa yom shloshim
oleh lekan ulekan, because it says in the משנה in this case,
day 30 counts in both directions. It ends the first one and
it begins the next one. Now the question is yes, it goes
in both directions, but your 30 days aren't over. So what's the
key principle to say why it worked for him on day 30?
מקצת היום ככולו. mikzat hayom kekulo. מאי היא? mai hi? What does
that mean? What underlies that explanation? מקצת היום ככולו. mikzat hayom kekulo.
Ultimately it's telling you that part of the day counts. הא אמר
חדא זימנא. ha amar chada zimna. We already learned that from the
easier case, one unit. Why are you telling me the exact same
הלכה halacha again by back-to-back units? You already told me that principle
that בדיעבד bedi'avad day 30 works. מהו דתימא, mahu detaima, I might
have thought, הני מילי לעניין חדא נזירות, hani mili le'inyan chada nezirut,
maybe you can use a half a day to count as a
whole day for one, אבל לשתי נזירות לא, aval lishtei nezirut lo,
you can't double dip, right? So it's one thing to say look,
even if you think about the conceptual principle, if I say מקצת
היום ככולו, mikzat hayom kekulo, it means I got a little bit
into day 30, it was like I finished day 30. Okay, we'll
say you finished day 30 in your נזירות. nezirut But if you
finished day 30 in your נזירות nezirut, number one, how can you
also say you started נזירות nezirut number two during it? Right? If
the whole logic is we're looking at it as if you finished
that day and you did the whole day of your נזירות, nezirut.
so it's not you're not able to start your second... that really
is a חידוש chiddush that you can say מקצת היום ככולו mikzat
hayom kekulo both ways, a little bit counted as full 30 and
then we'll say you get to now start fresh and it's like
you accepted your נזירות in the middle of a day and now
you can start your second
נזירות. So bottom line is בר פדא Bar Pada says does not
hold of מקצת היום ככולו. miktzas hayom kekulo. He says it's 29
days. You can never cut into the 29 days. You don't say
מקצת היום. miktzas hayom. You always have to bring it on day
30. Maybe לכתחילה lechatchila we'd ask you to bring it on day
31 because of times when people would say a month, but in
principle day 30 is when you should be bringing it. And רב
מתנא Rav Masna says no, no, no. In principle it's 30 days.
But so therefore we would like you to wait till day 31,
till the full 30 days to be over. But בדיעבד, bedieved, you
can do it on day 30 itself and even start a new
one on day 30 itself based on the מקצת היום ככולו miktzas
hayom kekulo principle.
Okay, so we'll just add.